Minesh Mathew

Summary

I am a Computer Vision researcher who has primarily been working on document image understanding problems. Presently, I work as a machine learning scientist at Wadhwani AI where I lead ML teams solving problems in public health space using computer vision, NLP and document image analysis.

Work experience

Machine learning scientist - Wadhwani AI

April 2023 - present

I lead the following teams: i) real time disease surveillance using health events reported in online news articles, ii) media surveillance for agriculture-realted articles, iii) using table understanding and OCR for extracting drug adherence information from handwritten forms and iv) development of language technologies such as OCR, speech-to-text, text-to-speech and machine translation for a externely low resource language and thereby contributing to the preservation of manuscripts and other cultureal artefacts.

Graduate research assistant - CVIT, IIIT Hyderabad

Jan 2016 - present

Coordinating document understanding projects and mentoring Master's and undergraduate students and interns.

Trainee Engineer - CVIT, IIIT Hyderabad

Apr 2013 - Jan 2016

Worked as part of a government of India project to build OCRs for Indian languages. My responsibilities included i) Coordinating annotations efforts and the data quality review process, ii) Building RNN based segmentation-free OCR pipeline for Malayalam OCR, iii) Maintaining a web based demo for RNN-based demo OCR service for 10+ Indian languages and iv) Leading an Audio books project that make use of Indian languages OCR and TTS for creating audio books in DAISY format

Skill development Executive - ASAP Kerala

Jan 2011 - Apr 2011

ASAP is an initiative by the Government of Kerala to increase the employability of Higher Secondary and undergrad students in government schools/colleges. My job was to help the students improve their basic communication and IT skills, and to equip them for the next levels in the training

Business Analyst - S&P Global Market Intelligence (Capital IQ)

Jun 2009 - Jun 2011

I worked as part of the Financial Estimates team. We were responsible for building and maintaining tools for collection of data from financial estimates. My work included collecting requirements from the clients and translating it into software design documents and most importantly to work as a liaison between the tech team and the clients/users.

Career break

Indian civil service exam attempt

Jun 2011 - Jan 2013

I spent nearly 18 months preparing and appearing for Indian civil service examination. I appeared for the prelims and mains exams in the year 2012.

Education

$2016 \mathrm{Jan} - 2023 \mathrm{Mar}$	PhD Computer Science -	IIIT Hyderabad		(CGPA: 9.5)
2013 Jul - 2015 Dec	MS - Computer Science -	IIIT Hyderabad		(CGPA: 8.2)
2005 Jun - 2009 Apr	Btech - Computer Science	and Engineering -	NIT Warangal	(CGPA: 6.7)

Achievements and fellowships

2023	CVPR 2023 outstanding reviewer
2021	ICCV 2021 outstanding reviewer
2021	Selected for WACV doctoral consortium
2021	Selected for ICCV doctoral consortium
2017	Best Paper; Int'l Workshop on Arabic Script Analysis and Recognition (ASAR)

2016 Awarded TCS PhD fellowship

Professional/academic activities

- Reviewer for conferences ECCV '22, SIGGRAPH '22, CVPR '22, '23 and '24, WACV '21 and '22, ICDAR '21 and ICCV '21
- Reviewer for journals TMLR, Pattern Recognition, IEEE TNNLS, TPAMI, IJCV, Visual Computer, Concurrency n' comput., and Engineering science and tech.
- 2024 Challenge chair, National Conference on Computer Vision, Pattern Recognition, Image Processing, and Graphics (NCVPRIPG) 2024.
- 2024 Organizer, ICDAR 2024 challenge on occluded scene text.
- 2023 Organizer, Competition on Text-based Video Question Answering on News Videos, ICDAR 2023
- 2023 Organizer, Competition on RoadText Video Text Detection, Tracking and Recognition, ICDAR 2023
- 2021 Organizer, Document Visual Question Answering Workshop and challenge ICDAR 2021
- 2020 Organizer and competition chair, Text and documents workshop and DocVQA challenge, CVPR 2020
- 2019 Organizer, Scene text VQA challenge, ICDAR 2019
- 2016-18 Organizer, Computer vision summer schools at IIIT Hyderabad

Talks and presentations

- August 2024 Invited talk at SOSCON (Samsung Open Source Conference) India 2024.
- July 2024 Tutorial on 'LLMs for information extraction from visually rich PDFs and document images', NCVPRIPG 2024, Thiruvananthapuram.
- May 2024 AI readiness workshop at Piramal workshop, Guwahati.
- Nov 2023 AI-readiness workshop at IIPH Gandhinagar
- 2022 DocVQA, Amex AI-CVIT workshop
- 2017 Sequence learning using RNNs, Computer vision summer school, IIIT Hyderabad
- 2017 Text recognition for Indian languages. CIE, IIIT Hyderabad startups meet
- 2016 Indian languages audio books using OCR and TTS, 'Technology for the visually impaired' seminar at University of Hyderabad
- 2013 Audio books playback app demonstration at various schools and State Council of Education Research and Training(SCERT) Kerala.

Skills

Programming Python, Matlab

ML/CV libraries Pytorch, OpenCV, Numpy

References

Available on request.

Publications

Total citations: 1359; h-index=15; i10-index=19 source: Google Scholar as on August 10, 2024

Journals

1. **Minesh Mathew**, Lluis Gomez, Dimosthenis Karatzas, CV Jawahar, Asking quetions on Handwritten Document Collections - Int'l journal on Document Analysis and Recognition (IJDAR); ICDAR-IJDAR special issue 2021 Springer preprint

$Conference/workshop\ publications$

 Minesh Mathew, Ajoy Mondal and CV Jawahar, Towards Deployable OCR Models for Indic Languages - ICPR 2024

- 2. Soumya Jahagirdar, **Minesh Mathew**, Dimosthenis Karatzas and CV Jawahar, Watching the News: Towards VideoQA Models that can Read WACV 2023 link
- 3. Sergi Garcia-Bordils, George Tom, Sangeeth Reddy, **Minesh Mathew**, Marçal Rusiñol, CV Jawahar and Dimosthenis Karatzas, *Read While You Drive-Multilingual Text Tracking on the Road* DAS 2022 link
- 4. **Minesh Mathew**, Viraj Bagal, Ruben Perez Tito, D Karatzas, Ernest Valveny and CV Jawahar, *Infographic VQA* WACV 2022 link
- 5. Minesh Mathew, D Karatzas and CV Jawahar, DocVQA: A Dataset for VQA on Document Images WACV 2021 link
- 6. Ruben Tito*, **Minesh Mathew***, CV Jawahar, Ernest Valveny and Dimosthenis Karatzas, *ICDAR 2021 Competition on Document Visual Question Answering* ICDAR 2021 (Competition report) link
- 7. Yash Khare, Viraj Bagal, **Minesh Mathew**, A Devi, UD Priyakumar and CV Jawahar, *MMBERT: Multimodal BERT Pretraining for Improved Medical VQA* ISBI 2021 link
- 8. **Minesh Mathew**, Ruben Tito , Dimosthenis Karatzas and R Manmatha and CV Jawahar, *DocVQA Challenge 2020* DAS 2020 (short paper) link
- 9. Sangeeth Reddy, **Minesh Mathew**, Lluis Gomez, Marcal Rusinol, Dimosthenis Karatzas and CV Jawahar, RoadText-1K: Text Detection & Recognition Dataset for Driving Videos ICRA 2020 link
- Ali Furkan Biten, Ruben Tito, Andres Mafla, Lluis Gomez, Marçal Rusinol, Minesh Mathew, CV Jawahar, Ernest Valveny and Dimosthenis Karatzas, ICDAR 2019 competition on scene text visual question answering - ICDAR 2019 (competition report) link
- 11. Deepayan Das, Jerin Philip, **Minesh Mathew** and CV Jawahar, A Cost Efficient Approach to Correct OCR Errors in Large Document Collections ICDAR 2019 link
- 12. Kartik Dutta, **Minesh Mathew**, Praveen Krishnan and CV Jawahar, *Localizing and Recognizing Text in Lecture Videos* ICFHR 2018 link
- 13. Kartik Dutta, Praveen Krishnan, **Minesh Mathew** and CV Jawahar, *Improving cnn-rnn hybrid networks for hand-writing recognition* ICFHR 2018 link
- 14. Kartik Dutta, Praveen Krishnan, **Minesh Mathew** and CV Jawahar, *Towards Spotting and Recognition of Handwritten Words in Indic Scripts* ICFHR 2018 link
- 15. Kartik Dutta, Praveen Krishnan, **Minesh Mathew** and CV Jawahar, Offline Handwriting Recognition on Devanagari Using a New Benchmark Dataset DAS 2018 link
- 16. Minesh Mathew, Mohit Jain and CV Jawahar, Benchmarking scene text recognition in Devanagari, Telugu and Malayalam MOCR workshop, ICDAR 2017 link
- 17. Mohit Jain, **Minesh Mathew** and CV Jawahar, *Unconstrained scene text and video text recognition for Arabic script* ASAR workshop 2017 link
- 18. Mohit Jain, **Minesh Mathew** and CV Jawahar, *Unconstrained ocr for urdu using deep cnn-rnn hybrid networks* ACPR 2017 link
- 19. VS Vinitha, **Minesh Mathew** and CV Jawahar, An Empirical Study of Effectiveness of Post-processing in Indic Scripts MOCR workshop ICDAR 2017 link
- 20. Kartik Dutta, Praveen Krishnan, **Minesh Mathew** and CV Jawahar, *Towards accurate handwritten word recognition* for Hindi and Bangla NCVPRIPG 2017 link
- 21. Minesh Mathew, AK Singh and CV Jawahar, Multilingual OCR for Indic Scripts DAS 2016 link